Register of the Béla Csejtey papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Béla Csejtey papers
1592-2004
1914-1991
2012C46
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (2.5 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, genealogical materials, personal documents, printed matter, memorabilia, and maps relating to the Csejtey family, military history, and Hungarian émigré affairs.
Csejtey, Béla, 1934-
Access
Collection is open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
Vitéz Béla Csejtey interview transcript, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Béla Csejtey Jr., a Hungarian émigré to the United States, was a geologist and historian. A refugee from Hungary following the revolution of 1956, Csejtey received his doctorate from Princeton University and spent most of his life working as a geologist, first in Antarctica, and later at the Alaskan branch of the US Geological Survey in Menlo Park, California. The US Board on Geographic Names recognized his distinguished service in Antarctica by naming a mountain in the Geologists' Range Mount Csejtey in his honor.
Csejtey's other passion was history, both family history and the history of the Hungarian forces on the front lines of World War I and the Kassa bombing of World War II. Csejtey’s father, Béla Csejtey Sr., served in both World Wars and earned medals of honor from the Kassa bombing and the battle of the Piave River in the north of Italy. Csejtey Jr. had a particular interest in this battle, where the Austro-Hungarian offensive suffered a decisive defeat in the first days of the summer of 1918. Hungarian regiments, which were disproportionately used in the fighting, lost tens of thousands of men. Csejtey Jr. spent years researching the literature and archives on the Piave River battle and combed the fields along the Piave with a metal detector to discover remains of the battle, some of which accompanied his papers into the Hoover Institution Archives.
Csejtey died in Palo Alto, California, in 2012.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Béla Csejtey papers are comprised of writings, correspondence, genealogical materials, personal documents, printed matter, maps, and memorabilia relating to military history, Hungarian émigré affairs, and the Csejtey family, particularly Béla Csejtey Jr. and his father, Béla Csejtey Sr.
Csejtey family.; Hungarians--United States.
- Biographical File, 1592-1978 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Comprised of documents related to the personal lives of Béla Csejtey Sr. and Jr., as well as the Csejtey family generally.
  - Béla Csejtey Sr.
    - Application for employment, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Asylum letter, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Biography, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Birth certificate, 1896 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Death records, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Personal notes, undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Photograph of medals, undated (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Proof of military service, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Béla Csejtey Jr.
    - Article, Mt. Csejtey, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Biography, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Mt. Csejtey, naming, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - General
    - Family research book, 1592-1918 (Box-folder 1: 12)
      Consists of Bela Csejtey Jr.'s research on the Csejtey family lineage dating back to 1592. Includes maps tracking family migration and historical photographs of the family.
    - Genealogy, undated (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Correspondence, 1960-1985 (Box 1)
  Includes incoming and outgoing letters between Béla Csejtey Jr. and his relatives. Primarily in Hungarian; arranged chronologically by date received.
  - 1960-1970 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - 1970-1975 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - 1975-1980 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - 1980-1985 (Box-folder 1: 17)
- Subject File, 1914-2004 (Boxes 2-3)
  Includes Béla Csejtey Jr.'s research and notes on the Piave battle in World War I and the Kassa bombing in World War II. There are two hardbound books, which include a published version of Csejtey Jr.'s research pertaining to both battles. Also included are World War I military handbooks and anti-communist books from World War II. The bulk of the documents are in Hungarian and Italian.
  - World War I, 1918-2004
    - Articles, 1975-1985 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Battle notes and research, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Military diary and translation, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Piave battle research book, 2004 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Research notes, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - World War II, 1940-1991
    - Felnagyitott terkep, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Katona Karpatokban, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Ludovika Akademia, 1941-1991 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Maps, undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Military documents (copies), 1940-1945 (Box-folder 2: 10-11)
  - Military materials, 1914-1945 (Box 3)
    Comprised of military regiment histories, periodicals, memoirs, and handbooks. The handbooks include handwritten notes made within the margins, as well as official military regiment letters sent between commanders.
    - A Katonai Bunvadi, 1944
    - Fegyelmi Szabalyzat, 1914
    - Hatalyos Jogszabalyai, 1934
    - Hidverok, 1945
    - Ideiglenes Szabalyzt, 1914
    - Ideiglenes Szamara, 1914
    - Ideiglenes Utasitas, 1914
    - Military forms, undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Military memoranda, 1925-1945
    - Perrendtartasa, 1917
    - Szervi Hatarozvanyok, 1914
    - Ugyviteli Szabalyzat, 1914
- Printed Matter, 1914-1997 (Boxes 4-5)
  - Benyovszky notes, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Book catalogues, 1965-1980 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Magyar Katona a Karpatokban, 1930 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Honved Luvokia Akademia, 1930 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Magyar Tuzer, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Maps, circa 1914-1945
    The maps, organized alphabetically, cover a range of European countries during World War I and World War II and include handwritten notes regarding the geographical locations of battle sites.
    - Austria, undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Austro-Hungary, undated (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
    - Belarus, undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - Central Europe, undated (Box-folder 5: 5-6)
    - Italy, undated (Box-folder 5: 7-8)
    - Poland, undated (Box-folder 5: 9-11)
    - Slovenia, undated (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1959-1997
    Includes clippings from Nemzetor, DUMA, Magyarsag, and The Eighth Tribe, among others. The clippings cover the experience of Hungarian immigrants following their escape from communism in 1956 and their acclimation into American culture, political news from the Hungarian Parliament in Budapest, and achievements ofthe Hungarian-American community. Arranged alphabetically by publication title. In Hungarian and English.
    - A-D, 1975-1985 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - I-M, 1965-1997 (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - E-H, 1970-1985 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - N-Q, 1967-1981 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - R-Z, 1959-1991 (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Oversize Material, 1978 (Box 6)
  Contains a framed case of artifacts, excavated by Béla Csejtey Jr. in 1978, from the Piave River Battle fought in Northern Italy during World War I.